Guide to the Eleanor M. Tilton Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Eleanor M. Tilton Papers,
1770-1991
Tilton, Eleanor M. (Eleanor Marguerite), 1913-
68 linear ft. (ca.93,000 items in 81 boxes, 58 file drawers, 88 card file boxes & 1 oversized folder).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4079404
Biographical Note
Professor of English, Barnard College, 1959-1979, scholar of American literature, editor & authority on Ralph W. Emerson. Columbia University Ph.D., 1947.
Scope and Content
This collection includes nine letters of Ralph Waldo Emerson as well as letters of Louis Agassiz, Amos Bronson Alcott, Oliver Wendell Holmes, Sr., Henry Wadsworth Longfellow, James Russell Lowell, John Lothrop Motley, Charles Sumner, and John Greenleaf Whittier. In addition, there are two incomplete manuscripts by Emerson and one document from the Liverpool Custom-house signed by Nathaniel Hawthorne as Consul for the United States. The collection also includes the corrected typescript, index, and page and galley proofs for Thomas Franklin Currier, A Bibliography of Oliver Wendell Holmes (New York, 1953) which was edited by Professor Tilton. Also, some early correspondence and photographs of the Tilton family and friends. There are letters from the actors Annie Louise Ames, Richard J. Dillon, and Hans L. Meery to Tilton's grandfather, Bernard Paul Verne, as well as photographs, tintypes, and daguerreotypes of the Verne family and friends.
1992 Addition: Her professional papers include correspondence, manuscripts, notes, and printed materials on many aspects of 18th and 19th century American literature, especially literary New England. Among her papers are files compiled in editing volumes 7 and 8 of The Letters of Ralph Waldo Emerson (New York, 1939-1991). These files contain correspondence, card files, notes, transcripts, photocopies, book typescripts, printed materials, and other related items. There are also similar files relating to Oliver Wendell Holmes, Sr. and to her books, Amiable Autocrat: A Biography of Dr. Oliver Wendell Holmes (New York, 1947) and Literary Bantlings: Addenda to the Holmes Bibliography (New York, 1957).
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 10 series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Series II: Cataloged Manuscripts
Series III: Cataloged Documents
Series IV: Photographs and Tintypes
Series V: General Files
Series VI: Subject Files
Series VII: Printed Materials
Series VIII: Ralph Waldo Emerson Files
Series IX: Henry David Thoreau Files
Series X: Oversize - General Files
Subjects
Barnard College--Faculty.; Ticknor and Fields.; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873.; Airy, George Biddell, Sir, 1801-1892.; Alcott, Amos Bronson, 1799-1888.; Ames, Annie Louise.; Badeau, Adam, 1831-1895.; Baker, George Melville, 1832-1890.; Brown, Charles Brockden, 1771-1810.; Bryant, Jacob, 1715-1804.; Bugbee, James M. (James McKellar), 1837-1913.; Burnap, Beniamin, fl.1700.; Burnap, Joseph, fl.1700.; Currier, Thomas Franklin.; Dillon, Richard J.; Eatton, John.; Emerson, Ralph Waldo, 1803-1882.; Emerson family.; Fields, James Thomas, 1817-1881.; Fowles, John, 1926-2005.; Gillett, Frederick Huntington, 1851-1935.; Gunn, Elisha, fl.1796.; Gunn, William, fl.1796.; Hawthorne, Nathaniel, 1804-1864.; Henley, Samuel, 1740-1815.; Hinman, R. R. (Royal Ralph), 1785-1868.; Hoar, Elizabeth Sherman, 1814-1878.; Hoar family.; Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1809-1894.; Howison, George Holmes, 1834-1917.; Ireland, Alexander, 1810-1894.; Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth, 1807-1882.; Lowell, James Russell, 1819-1891.; Luce, Clare Boothe, 1903-1987.; Markham, Edwin, 1852-1940.; Meery, Hans L.; Motley, John Lothrop, 1814-1877.; Nickools, Thomas, fl.1700.; Phipps, Samuel, fl.1700.; Quay, Matthew Stanley, 1833-1904.; Richardson, John, fl.1700.; Root, Elisha, fl.1796.; Root, Joseph, fl.1796.; Root, Martin, fl.1796.; Smith, Gerrit, 1797-1874.; Sumner, Charles, 1811-1874.; Thoreau, Henry David, 1817-1862.; Tilton family.; Verne, Bernard Paul.; Ward, Samuel Gray.; Ward family.; Weiss, John, 1818-1879.; Whipple, Edwin Percy, 1819-1886.; Whittier, John Greenleaf, 1807-1892.; Wilson, Carroll A. (Carroll Atwood), 1886-1947.; Actors.; American letters--Editing.; American literature.; Criticism, Textual.; Letters--Editing.; Literature publishing.; Scholarly publishing.; Theater--Massachusetts--Boston--19th century.; Transcendentalists (New England); Advertisements.; Announcements.; Applications.; Articles.; Bibliographies.; Biographies.; Brochures.; Bulletins.; Calendars.; Card files.; Catalogs (trade).; Certificates.; Clippings.; Contracts.; Curricula vitae.; Daguerreotypes.; Deeds.; Dissertations.; Drafts (literary).; Engravings.; Essays.; Etchings.; Examinations.; Financial documents and records.; Galley proofs.; Genealogies.; Greeting cards.; Guidebooks.; Illustrations.; Indexes.; Invitations.; Invoices.; Lists.; Lithographs.; Manuscripts (literary).; Maps.; Newsletters.; Notebooks.; Notes.; Pamphlets.; Photographs.; Photoprints.; Pictures.; Playbills.; Poems.; Portraits.; Postcards.; Prints.; Proofs.; Reports.; Reprints.; Reviews.; Sermons.; Ship's papers.; Silhouettes.; Syallabi.; Tax returns.; Tintypes.; Transcripts.; Actors.; Actresses.; Authors.; Editors.; Philosophers.; Physicians.; Poets.; Scholars.; Women college teachers.; Women scholars.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
1979 M-79 Tilton, Eleanor M. Gift
Gift of Eleanor M. Tilton, 1979, 1983, & 1992.
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  - Agassiz, Louis (Box 1)
  - Airy, Sir George Biddell (Box 1)
  - Alcott, Bronson (Box 1)
  - Ames, Annie Louise (Box 1)
  - Baker, George Melville (Box 1)
  - Bryant, Jacob (Box 1)
  - Dillon, Richard J. (Box 1)
  - Emerson, Ralph Waldo (Box 1)
  - Fields, James Thomas (Box 1)
  - Fowles, John (Box 1)
  - Gillett, Frederick Huntington (Box 1)
  - Hinman, Royal Ralph (Box 1)
  - Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1809-1894 (Box 1)
  - Howison, George Holmes (Box 1)
  - Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth (Box 1)
  - Lowell, James Russell (Box 1)
  - Luce, Clare Boothe (Box 1)
  - Markham, Edwin (Box 1)
  - Meery, Hans L. (Box 1)
  - Motley, John Lothrop (Box 1)
  - Quay, Matthew Stanley (Box 1)
  - Ripley, Aiden Lasell (Box 1)
  - Sumner, Charles (Box 1)
  - Whipple, Edwin Percy (Box 1)
  - Whittier, John Greenleaf (Box 1)
  - Wilson, Carroll (Box 1)
- Series II: Cataloged Manuscripts
  - Emerson, Ralph Waldo (Box 1)
- Series III: Cataloged Documents
  - Hawthorne, Nathaniel (Box 1)
- Series IV: Photographs and Tintypes
  - Verne family & friends (Box 1)
- Series V: General Files
  - Correspondence: A-Z (Box 2)
  - Financial (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous manuscripts & notes (Box 4)
- Series VI: Subject Files
  Including correspondence, manuscripts, documents & printed materials
  - Adams family (Box 4)
  - Alcott family (Box 4)
  - Brown, Charles Brockden (Box 4)
  - Bryant, William Cullen (Box 4)
  - Carlyle, Alexander (Box 5)
  - Coleridge, Samuel Taylor (Box 5)
  - Columbia University (Box 5)
  - Curriculum Vitae (Box 5)
  - Dennet, John Richard (Box 5)
  - D'Evelyn, Charlotte (Box 5)
  - Donne, John (Box 5)
  - The Edinburgh Review (Box 6)
  - Emerson, Ralph Waldo (Box 6)
    [See Boxes 12-72]
  - English 75 (course) (Box 6)
  - English 76 (course) (Box 6)
  - English 97 & 98 (courses) (Box 6)
  - Hawthorne, Nathaniel (Box 6)
  - Holmes, Oliver Wendell (Box 6)
    [See Boxes 73-81]
  - Howells, William Dean (Box 6)
  - Hume & other philosophers (Box 6)
  - Irving, Washington (Box 6)
  - James, Henry (Box 7)
  - Maps (Box 7)
  - Melville, Herman (Box 7)
  - Mount Holyoke College (Box 7)
  - Office description (Box 7)
  - "Old News" - her student paper & notes re. William Parks & The Virginia Gazette (Box 7)
  - Pictorial/picturesque (Box 8)
  - Poe, Edgar Allen (Box 8)
  - Politics (Box 8)
  - Prosody & rhetoric/English 75 (course) (Box 8)
  - Recommendations (Box 9)
  - Reviews (Box 9)
  - Reviews by Tilton (Box 9)
  - Romantics (Box 9)
  - Szell, Timea K. (Box 9)
  - Taylor, Edward, d. 1729 (Box 9)
  - Taylor, Edward, d. 1729 (Box 9)
  - Thoreau, Henry David (Box 9)
    [See Box 82]
  - Winthrop, John & Thomas Prince (Box 9)
  - Wordsworth, William (Box 9)
- Series VII: Printed Materials
  - Articles, offprints, periodicals (Box 10)
  - Books, photocopies & oversize (Box 11)
- Series VIII: Ralph Waldo Emerson Files
  - Subseries VIII.1: Book Manuscripts of The Letters of Ralph Waldo Emerson
    - Typescripts: pp. 1-555 (Box 12)
    - Typescripts: pp. 556-1335 (Box 13)
    - Typescripts: pp. 1336-1891 (Box 14)
    - Typescripts: pp. 1892-2207 (Box 15)
    - Typescripts: pp. 2208-2757 (Box 16)
    - Typescripts: pp. 2758-3133 (Box 17)
    - Typescripts: pp. 3134-3487 (Box 18)
    - Typescripts: pp. 3487-5902 (Box 19)
    - Book proofs (Box 20)
    - Book proofs (Box 21)
  - Subseries VIII.2: Card Files re. Emerson and Holmes
    All shelved Off-Site
    - A-Z, (1 Card file box) (Box 1-A)
    - 1975-1976; Through 1851 [loose notebook pages]; From 1852; & Misc., (1 Card file box) (Box 1-B)
    - 3 misc. files, (1 Card file box) (Box 1-C)
    - 4 misc. files, (1 Card file box) (Box 1-D)
    - Misc., (1 Card file box) (Box 2)
    - Owners & freq. citations, (1 Card file box) (Box 3)
    - Owners & freq. citations, (1 Card file box) (Box 3-A)
    - Library of RWE: A-K, (1 Card file box) (Box 4)
    - Library of RWE: L-Z, (1 Card file box) (Box 5)
    - Summaries of Letters, 1848-1853, (1 Card file box) (Box 6)
    - Summaries of Letters, 1854-1864, (1 Card file box) (Box 7)
    - Summaries of Letters, 1812-1847, (1 Card file box) (Box 8)
    - Summaries of Letters, 1812-1847, (1 Card file box) (Box 8-A)
    - Summaries of Letters, 1865-n.d., (1 Card file box) (Box 9)
    - Summaries of Letters, 1865-n.d., (1 Card file box) (Box 9-A)
    - List of Recipients, 1803-1840, (1 Card file box) (Box 10)
    - List of Recipients, 1803-1840, (1 Card file box) (Box 10-A)
    - List of Recipients, 1840-1849, (1 Card file box) (Box 11)
    - List of Recipients, 1840-1849, (1 Card file box) (Box 11-A)
    - List of Recipients, 1850-1859, (1 Card file box) (Box 12)
    - List of Recipients, 1850-1859, (1 Card file box) (Box 12-A)
    - List of Recipients, 1860-1870, (1 Card file box) (Box 13)
    - List of Recipients, 1860-1870, (1 Card file box) (Box 13-A)
    - List of Recipients, 1871-1883 & n.d., (1 Card file box) (Box 14)
    - List of Recipients, 1871-1883 & n.d., (1 Card file box) (Box 14-A)
    - N.d. dated & towns & lectures [& misc.], (1 Card file box) (Box 15)
    - N.d. dated & towns & lectures [& misc.], (1 Card file box) (Box 15-A)
    - Brief index notes: A-B, (1 Card file box) (Box 16)
    - Brief index notes: C-E, (1 Card file box) (Box 17)
    - Brief index notes: F-J, (1 Card file box) (Box 18)
    - Brief index notes: F-J, (1 Card file box) (Box 18-A)
    - Brief index notes: K-O, (1 Card file box) (Box 19)
    - Brief index notes: P-S, (1 Card file box) (Box 20)
    - Brief index notes: P-S, (1 Card file box) (Box 20-A)
    - Brief index notes: T-Z, (1 Card file box) (Box 21)
    - Full index notes: A-A[Z], (1 Card file box) (Box 22)
    - Full index notes: A-A[Z], (1 Card file box) (Box 22-A)
    - Full index notes: A-A[Z], (1 Card file box) (Box 22-B)
    - Full index notes: BA-Burnouf, (1 Card file box) (Box 23)
    - Full index notes: BA-Burnouf, (1 Card file box) (Box 23-A)
    - Full index notes: BA-Burnouf, (1 Card file box) (Box 23-B)
    - Full index notes: [Burns]-CO[NV], (1 Card file box) (Box 24)
    - Full index notes: [Burns]-CO[NV], (1 Card file box) (Box 24-A)
    - Full index notes: [Burns]-CO[NV], (1 Card file box) (Box 24-B)
    - Full index notes: C[ONW]-El[i] Emer[son], (1 Card file box) (Box 25)
    - Full index notes: C[ONW]-El[i] Emer[son], (1 Card file box) (Box 25-A)
    - Full index notes: C[ONW]-El[i] Emer[son], (1 Card file box) (Box 25-B)
    - Full index notes: Ellen E[merson]-E[therwald], (1 Card file box) (Box 26)
    - Full index notes: Ellen E[merson]-E[therwald], (1 Card file box) (Box 26-A)
    - Full index notes: Ellen E[merson]-E[therwald], (1 Card file box) (Box 26-B)
    - Full index notes: Eth[ic]-G[rec], (1 Card file box) (Box 27)
    - Full index notes: Eth[ic]-G[rec], (1 Card file box) (Box 27-A)
    - Full index notes: Eth[ic]-G[rec], (1 Card file box) (Box 27-B)
    - Full index notes: Greece-[C.] Hubbard, (1 Card file box) (Box 28)
    - Full index notes: Greece-[C.] Hubbard, (1 Card file box) (Box 28-A)
    - Full index notes: Greece-[C.] Hubbard, (1 Card file box) (Box 28-B)
    - Full index notes: [W.] Hu[bbard]-Lecture [Green], (1 Card file box) (Box 29)
    - Full index notes: [W.] Hu[bbard]-Lecture [Green], (1 Card file box) (Box 29-A)
    - Full index notes: Lecture [H]-[LY], (1 Card file box) (Box 30)
    - Full index notes: Lecture [H]-[LY], (1 Card file box) (Box 30-A)
    - Full index notes: Lecture [H]-[LY], (1 Card file box) (Box 30-B)
    - Full index notes: MA-NAT, (1 Card file box) (Box 31)
    - Full index notes: MA-NAT, (1 Card file box) (Box 31-A)
    - Full index notes: MA-NAT, (1 Card file box) (Box 31-B)
    - Full index notes: NAV-P[LA], (1 Card file box) (Box 32)
    - Full index notes: NAV-P[LA], (1 Card file box) (Box 32-A)
    - Full index notes: NAV-P[LA], (1 Card file box) (Box 32-B)
    - Full index notes: PL[E]-ROM, (1 Card file box) (Box 33)
    - Full index notes: PL[E]-ROM, (1 Card file box) (Box 33-A)
    - Full index notes: RON-SL, (1 Card file box) (Box 34)
    - Full index notes: RON-SL, (1 Card file box) (Box 34-A)
    - Full index notes: SM-TR, (1 Card file box) (Box 35)
    - Full index notes: SM-TR, (1 Card file box) (Box 35-A)
    - Full index notes: SM-TR, (1 Card file box) (Box 35-B)
    - Full index notes: TU-Z, (1 Card file box) (Box 36)
    - Full index notes: TU-Z, (1 Card file box) (Box 36-A)
    - Full index notes: TU-Z, (1 Card file box) (Box 36-B)
    - Full index notes: Misc., (1 Card file box) (Box 37)
    - Full index notes: Misc., (1 Card file box) (Box 37-A)
    - Full index notes: Misc., (Card file box) (Box 37-B)
  - Subseries VIII.3: Correspondence re. Emerson
    - A-E (Box 22)
    - F-L (Box 23)
    - M-R (Box 24)
    - S-Z (Box 25)
  - Subseries VIII.4: Hoar Family of Concord, MA
    - Elizabeth Sherman Hoar, 1814-1879, fiancee of Charles C. Emerson (Box 26)
  - Subseries VIII.5: Notebooks re. Emerson
    - 1824-1875 & [n.d.] (Box 27)
    - By topics (Box 28)
    - Unlabeled or loose pages (Box 29)
  - Subseries VIII.6: Notes/Miscellaneous
    - Part 1 (Box 30)
    - Part 2 (Box 31)
    - Part 3 (Box 32)
    - Part 4 (Box 33)
  - Subseries VIII.7: Photocopies of Letteres to and from Emerson
    - 1811-1840 (Box 34)
    - 1840-1845 (Box 35)
    - 1845-1851 (Box 36)
    - 1852-1857 (Box 37)
    - 1858-1863 (Box 38)
    - 1864-1870 (Box 39)
    - 1871-1881 & Misc. (Box 40)
    - Various topics (1) (Box 41)
    - Various topics (2) (Box 42)
  - Subseries VIII.8: Printed Materials
    - Printed Materials (Box 43)
    - Photocopies (Box 44)
  - Subseries VIII.9: Subject Files
    - A-E (Box 45)
    - F-Le (Box 46)
    - Li-O (Box 47)
    - P-W (Box 48)
  - Subseries VIII.10: Transcripts of Letters to amd from Emerson
    - Transcripts made by Joel Myerson - 1 (Box 49)
    - Transcripts made by Joel Myerson - 2 (Box 50)
    - Transcripts & notes: 1807-1833 (Box 51)
    - Transcripts & notes: 1834-1838 (Box 52)
    - Transcripts & notes: 1839-1840 (Box 53)
    - Transcripts & notes: 1841-1843 (Box 54)
    - Transcripts & notes: 1844-1846 (Box 55)
    - Transcripts & notes: 1847-1849 (Box 56)
    - Transcripts & notes: 1850-1852 (Box 57)
    - Transcripts & notes: 1853-1855 (Box 58)
    - Transcripts & notes: 1856-1858 (Box 59)
    - Transcripts & notes: 1859-1861 (Box 60)
    - Transcripts & notes: 1861-1863 (Box 61)
    - Transcripts & notes: 1864-1865 (Box 62)
    - Transcripts & notes: 1866-1867 (Box 63)
    - Transcripts & notes: 1868-1869 (Box 64)
    - Transcripts & notes: 1870-1872 (Box 65)
    - Transcripts & notes: 1872-1874 (Box 66)
    - Transcripts & notes: 1875-1883 (Box 67)
    - Transcripts & notes: Miscellany (Box 68)
  - Subseries VIII.11: Typescripts re. Emerson
    - Part 1 (Box 69)
    - Part 2 (Box 70)
    - Part 3 (Box 71)
  - Subseries VIII.12: Ward Family of Boston
    - Samuel Gray Ward & Anna Hazard Barker Ward (Box 72)
  - Subseries VIII.13: Oliver Wendell Holmes, Sr.
    - A Bibliography of Oliver Wendell Holmes by Thomas Franklin Currier. Ed. by Eleanor M. Tilton, (Pages 1-700 Typescript) (Box 73)
    - A Bibliography of Oliver Wendell Holmes by Thomas Franklin Currier. Ed. by Eleanor M. Tilton, (Pages 701-1282 & Index Typescript) (Box 74)
    - A Bibliography of Oliver Wendell Holmes by Thomas Franklin Currier. Ed. by Eleanor M. Tilton, (Pages 1-600 Page proofs) (Box 75)
    - A Bibliography of Oliver Wendell Holmes by Thomas Franklin Currier. Ed. by Eleanor M. Tilton, (Pages 601-707 Pages proofs & Galley proofs) (Box 76)
    - A Bibliography of Oliver Wendell Holmes by Thomas Franklin Currier. Ed. by Eleanor M. Tilton, (Galley proofs) (Box 77)
  - Subseries VIII.14: Holmes Research Materials
    - Correspondence, printed materials, photographs, etc. (Box 78)
    - Manuscripts & notes - 1 (Box 79)
    - Manuscripts & notes - 2 (Box 80)
    - Manuscripts & notes - 3 (Box 81)
- Series IX: Henry David Thoreau Files
  - Correspondence re. Thoreau (Box 82)
  - John Brown & Harpers Ferry (Box 82)
  - Printed materials (Box 82)
  - The Thoreau Society Bulletin (Box 82)
  - Witherell, Elizabeth Hall Correspondence (Box 82)
  - Witherell, Elizabeth Hall The Poetry of henry David Thoreau: a Selected Critical Edition (Box 82)
- Series X: Oversize - General Files
  - Printed Materials - Books & photocopies (Box 386)